Aleksandar Milicevic

CONTACT Information Microsoft Corporation

9255 Towne Centre Dr, Ste 400

San Diego, CA 92121 USA

e-mail: almili@microsoft.com

web: https://aleksandarmilicevic.github.io

CURRENT POSITION

Senior Software Engineer at Microsoft in the *Tools for Software Engineers* Group

August, 2015 - present

Currently working on a modern build system that enables fast, reliable, distributed, cacheable, and incremental builds for projects ranging from single-developer apps to large-scale enterprise systems.

Filesystem Virtualization for Linux. Lead role in designing, implementing, and optimizing a virtual filesystem for Linux that allows a client's filesystem to be mimicked on a remote server, overlaid on top of a server's local filesystem, with client files being uploaded selectively and ondemand, as soon as they become needed. (FUSE, OverlayFs, Posix, gRPC, C++, C#)

Process Sandboxing and Substitution for Linux. Lead role in designing, implementing, and optimizing a library for dynamically observing (and preventing undesired) file accesses of a process, as well as substituting its select child processes and executing them in a virtual filesystem on a remote server. (LD_PRELOAD, rtld-audit, C++, C#, Azure VMs)

Process Sandboxing for macOS. One of two main contributors to a process sandboxing library implemented as a kernel extension for macOS. Designed/implemented a concurrent lock-free trie data structure, used it to implement layers of caching for the code running in kernel mode, resulting in a 35% performance increase. (Kext, KAuth, TrustedBsd, C++, C#)

Debugger and Query Language for Analyzing Build Logs. Designed/implemented a first-order relational query language for conveniently analyzing build logs data and graphically representing the results in a VSCode debugger session. (VSCode Extension; C#, TypeScript)

Extend a Build Engine to Support Daemon Processes. Argued strongly for developing a generic support instead of hardcoding an ad-hoc implementation for a single use case we had at a time. This is atypical for build engines, which can typically only run a process after all its dependencies have completed. In some rare cases, mostly for performance reasons, it is useful to have a process (e.g., a service, or a daemon) that runs throughout the build. The argument prevailed, I designed the abstractions, implemented the original use case, and observed a 90% reduction in build tail time. By now several more use cases have benefited from this technology. (C#)

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Declarative programming, specification languages, executable specifications, programming languages, connecting high-level specifications with low-level code, formal methods, software verification, program synthesis, program analysis, software engineering.

EDUCATION

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts USA

Ph.D., Computer Science, May 2015

• Topic: "Advancing Declarative Programming" (advised by Prof. Daniel Jackson)

M.S., Computer Science, September 2010

• Topic: "Executable Specifications for Java Programs" (advised by Prof. Daniel Jackson)

School of Electrical Engineering, Belgrade, Serbia

B.Sc. in Computer Science, November 2007

• Topic: Parallel Test Generation and Execution with Korat (advised by Prof. Dragan Milicev)

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA

Research Assistant August, 2008 - May 2015

 ${\bf Includes\ Ph.D.\ research\ Masters-level\ coursework\ and\ research\ projects.}$

Teaching Assistant Spring 2009, Fall 2009

"6.005 Elements of Software Construction": gave recitations, graded problem sets and projects.

RESEARCH Internships

Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA, USA

Research intern June, 20011 - August, 2011

Worked with Rustan Leino on program synthesis from first-order declarative specifications.

Microsoft Research Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom

Research intern June, 2009 - August, 2009

Worked with Hillel Kugler on analyzing and executing Live Sequence Charts using SMT.

University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, Urbana, Illinois, USA

Visiting Scholar August, 2006 - September, 2006

Worked with Darko Marinov on bounded-exhaustive test input generation.

Industry Experience

Serbian Object Laboratories, Belgrade, Serbia

Software Engineer

March, 2006 - August, 2008

Actively worked on the development of the EDMT Server (www.bmmsoft.com). Technologies used: WebWork, Java Servlets, WS, SOAP, JSP, HTML, CSS, JS, AJAX, with Sybase IQ database.

Google Inc., New York, New York, USA

Software Engineering Intern

July, 2007 - September, 2007

Worked with Nemanja Petrovic on decoding barcodes from images taken with a cell phone.

RESEARCH PROJECTS

- Alloy* (http://alloy.mit.edu/alloy/hola): a general-purpose, higher-order relational constraint solver (over bounded domains).
- αRby (http://people.csail.mit.edu/aleks/arby): an embedding of a declarative modeling/specification language (alloy) into an imperative object-oriented programming language (ruby).
- Squander (http://people.csail.mit.edu/aleks/squander): a unified environment for execution of declarative specification (written in first-order relational logic) and imperative Java code.
- Jennisys (http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/projects/jennisys): a programming language and a synthesis tool from declarative first-order specifications to imperative code.
- The Alloy Analyzer (http://alloy.mit.edu): an automated model finder for a first-order relational specification language.
- Korat (http://korat.sourceforge.net): a tool for bounded-exhaustive generation of test inputs based on complex constraints the inputs must satisfy.

Publications

- P. Nie, A. Çelik, M. Coley, **A. Milicevic**, J. Bell, M. Gligoric. Debugging the Performance of Maven's Test Isolation: Experience Report. *ISSTA 2020, Los Angeles, USA*
- B. Buhse, T. Wei, Z. Zang, A. Milicevic, M. Gligoric. VeDebug: Regression Debugging Tool for Java ICSE Demo 2019, Montreal, Canada.
- A. Çelik, M. Vasic, **A. Milicevic**, M. Gligoric. Regression Test Selection Across JVM Boundaries. *FSE 2017, Paderborn, Germany.*

- M. Vasic, Z. Parvez, A. Milicevic, M. Gligoric. File-level vs. Module-level Regression Test Selection for .NET. FSE 2017 (Industry Track), Paderborn, Germany.
- E. Kang, A. Milicevic, D. Jackson. Multi-Representational Security Analysis, FSE 2016, Seattle, WA, USA. [Distinguished Paper Award]
- A. Çelik, A. Knaust, **A. Milicevic**, M. Gligoric. Build System with Lazy Retrieval for Java Projects, FSE 2016, Seattle, WA, USA.
- **A.** Milicevic. Advancing Declarative Programming, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Ph.D. Thesis, May 2015.
- **A.** Milicevic, J. P. Near, E. Kang, and D. Jackson. Alloy*: A Higher-Order Relational Constraint Solver, *ICSE 2015*, Florence, Italy. [Distinguished Paper Award]
- **A.** Milicevic, J. P. Near, E. Kang, and D. Jackson. Alloy*: A Higher-Order Relational Constraint Solver, MIT CSAIL Technical Report, September 2014.
- **A.** Milicevic, and D. Jackson. Preventing Arithmetic Overflows in Alloy (extended journal version), *Science of Computer Programming, May 2014.*
- **A.** Milicevic, I. Efrati, and D. Jackson. α Rby—An Embedding of Alloy in Ruby, *ABZ 2014, Toulouse, France.*
- **A.** Milicevic, M. Gligoric, D. Marinov, and D. Jackson. Model-Based, Event-Driven Programming Paradigm for Interactive Web Applications, *Onward!* 2013, *Indianapolis*, *Indiana*, *USA*
- K. R. M. Leino, and A. Milicevic. Program Extrapolation with Jennisys, *Splash 2012, Tucson, Arizona, USA*.
- A. Milicevic, and D. Jackson. Preventing Arithmetic Overflows in Alloy, ABZ 2012, Pisa, Italy.
- **A.** Milicevic, D. Rayside, K. Yessenov, and D. Jackson. Unifying Execution of Imperative and Declarative Code, *ICSE 2011, Waikiki, Honolulu, Hawaii*.
- J. P. Near, A. Milicevic, E. Kang, D. Jackson. A Lightweight Approach to Construction and Evaluation of a Dependability Case, *ICSE 2011*, Waikiki, Honolulu, Hawaii.
- **A.** Milicevic, and H. Kugler. Model Checking with SMT and Theory of Lists, 3rd NASA Formal Method Symposium (NFM 2011), Pasadena, California, USA.
- **A.** Milicevic. Executable Specifications for Java Programs, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Master's Thesis, September 2010.
- D. Rayside, A. Milicevic, K. Yessenov, G. Dennis, and D. Jackson. Agile Specifications, OOPSLA Onward! 2009 (short paper), Orlando, Florida, USA.
- D. Rayside, Z. Benjamin, J. Near, R. Sing, **A. Milicevic**, and D. Jackson. Equality and Hashing for (almost) Free: Generating Implementations from Abstraction Functions, *ICSE 2009, Vancouver, Canada*.
- S. Misailovic, A. Milicevic, N. Petrovic, S. Khurshid, and D. Marinov. Parallel Test Generation and Execution with Korat, ESEC/FSE 2007, Dubrovnik, Croatia.
- **A.** Milicevic, S. Misailovic, D. Marinov, and S. Khurshid. Korat: A Tool for Generating Structurally Complex Test Inputs, *ICSE Demo 2007, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA*.
- S. Misailovic, A. Milicevic, S. Khurshid, and D. Marinov. Generating Test Inputs for Fault-Tree Analyzers using Imperative Predicates, STEP 2007, Memphis, Tennessee, USA

CLASS PROJECTS

- Software model checking using the SMT Theory of Lists
 (Foundations of Program Analysis) Resulted in a publication in NFM'11.
- Puzzler May 2009
 (Natural Language Processing) Solver for natural-language logic puzzles (e.g., the famous Einstein puzzle) via a translation to formal relational logic and a use of an automated constraint solver for it. Done in collaboration with colleagues Joseph P. Near and Eunsuk Kang.
- Visual CPU simulator

 (Computer Architecture) Register Transfer Logic view, per-clock, per-instruction and per-program simulation advance, real-time register and memory modification, compiler from an assembly language. Done in collaboration with Ana Hadzievska, Dusan Matic, Milos Petrovic, Milos Siroka.
- Multithreading library for the 16-bit C++ compiler (Operating Systems) Java-like threading model for the 16-bit C++ compiler. Features: context switching, explicit synchronous preemption, asynchronous preemption (caused by an interrupt), time sharing, round-robin scheduling. Concepts: semaphores, events, mutexes, monitors.